What's up everybody? Luke Stratton from
Luke Stratton Designs. I'm here with
Jesse from Llama Mall. How's it going
Jesse? Great man. How you doing? Good.
Um, we had some downtime today here on
the third night of of the Boston run.
So, I wanted to, you know, give a new
rig rundown. We did a rig rundown. How
long ago was that? A couple years ago.
At least two years ago. Yeah. And it was
a, you know, the small room wasn't lit
very well. This is uh, you get the full
experience here today. So, I got a new
console that um, I put out earlier this
year. I call it the LPC full size. This
is the lighting performance controller.
It's designed to go to and from a Grand
MA full size almost without translation,
if you
will. Um, yeah. So, I guess let's uh dig
right in here. Okay. Cool. Cool. So,
here it is. LBC full size. It's
basically three APC20s. They're like a
Ableton device. Mhm. Uh, and this is a
programmable keyboard. Um, which has all
the X keys on it and all the programming
keys. They got a track ball and all the
necessary lighting hardware and whatnot.
Uh, but so I get a lot of questions
about actually how it's laid out like
and you know as a younger designer I
spent a lot of time like oh man if I
could just get like a screenshot or
picture of like Chris Cota show file
like that would be the thing you know
but the reality is that you find your
own way to do it and that's the way that
you do it. Um, but for the curious minds
I always think it's cool to have this
kind of stuff on the internet. So we're
going to go all the way down the rabbit
hole today. I would explain a ton of
stuff. It'll be a long, boring video for
some people, but it'll be like a really
cool video for a small group, and that's
what we're going for, right? Okay. So,
the way this guy's laid out, um, all
these all 30 faders down here, and I say
30 cuz these knobs are also mapped to
faders. All 30 faders and these buttons
above the faders, uh, correspond to the
30 faders on a Grand Mate full size. Um
so the split would be like right here in
the middle for the f first first 15 and
the second 15 and then above that above
this line right here uh I have uh grids
which are mapped to the touch screen. So
you can see like this grid represents uh
screen four and this grid is screen
three and this grid is screen two. Um,
and in this particular show file, these
two are locked, but then this first one
will change when I change pages in MA.
So, like I've got a color page here.
You'll see when I change the second
color page, this grid updates. So, that
lets me put as many things basically
infinite number of things here if I want
them. Um, so let's dive right in. Um, on
the first page, my main page is the
color page. Um, and the way I have it,
uh, basically is that this top, uh, row
is the full rig
on any given color. Um, and then I just
copy that sequence down and then apply a
world filter. So like here's magenta for
the full rig, but if I click uh here,
it'll be just the the low spots and
here's the high spots and here's upstage
and downstage. So, you know, at any
point I can punt in any new color
combination I want. So often I'll, you
know, be like kind of playing along if I
need to, you know, or um I've got a fade
time here for every color or gobo on the
on the console. So if I snap this guy
down, I can get a new look ready and
either just tap it in. Just tap it in.
Yeah. Or I can, you know, put another
look up and then increase the fade time
and it'll fade to the new look. So, I do
that a lot in the show. If I'm like,
"Okay, well, we got a big peak coming
up. I'm going to slow this down and I'm
going to turn this on. Got a color look
ready. I'm going to turn the prism on
and go to a new gobo. I can snap it in
and boom, it's ready to rock." Make
sense? So, that's the top here is is
main colors. And then I've got a a whole
assortment of goos, which you can see
here. I'll turn off the prism.
Um all whole assortment of goos here for
our robi
points. Uh and then this section here
are my four main pages that I use. And
then um patterns for the X4S's which you
can see those little guys up there. So I
can do some wipes and kind of different
patterns on the X4S's. Uh and then this
is a trigger for the flat prism. So this
is like with the the beam look on a
proby point. You turn this guy on, you
get that flat prism and I can rotate it
there. Um, down here in fader world, I
uh you saw a second ago, I got my color
rate here on this fader. It's just a a
rate master and MA and everything here
is assigned to it. And then I got my
specials. So I've got one for each guy
in the
band. Um, open fader right now. And then
this is my uh asymmetrical or excuse me,
symmetrical circle pan tilt effect. and
an
asymmetrical pan tilt effect. And this
guy's open right now. Room to grow.
Cool. So, for my second page, I have uh
I just call it color two. And it's kind
of a variation of each one of these
colors. So, on page one, I had like
magenta and red and yellow that on on
page two here, I've got uh still a
magenta on my points, but you get more
of a ruby color on the LEDs. See that
like rubiness? And this is like a burnt
warmer red. And then I've got like a
skin CTO color. Here's um an amber
color. So this is kind of just like a
variation. So if I'm tired of like doing
those same colors all night, I can
switch to the second page and get kind
of the same vibe but with a little bit
of variation. Right. Uh the third page
is wipes. And the way I do that is the
top wipes the whole rig from left to
right. And then from there, I kind of
divide it up where I've got um uh left
to right, both spots and
wash. And then down here was right to
left. So I can, you know, I can kind of
do this thing, wipe one way or if I want
to put a color combo in, I can. There's
a lot of playability here, so I like it
playable. Um and then my fourth page,
it's got a lot of room to grow, but uh
I've got a few effects here like this
zoom in effect.
Um, and then all my flipped colors are
here. So, when we're playing the song
flipped, I do these like half and half
kind of things for the rig. It's my
lighting interpretation for
flipped. Um, yeah. Cool. That's that's
the first APC. Any questions, Jesse? No.
No. Actually, it all makes a lot more
sense to me now that you've gone through
the different pages. Yeah. Cool. So, if
we dig into the second ABC20, which
represents uh kind of the middle fader
section, and then whatever I have going
on uh screen three, this is kind of the
meat of my my console layout. Um I've
got all my position movements up here,
and most of these are single cues. So, I
can go to like the down position here,
and I have my position fade times over
here. So, I'll crank that up for now.
Down. I got this one called blind up.
Um, some basic ones in, out, stage edge.
If I double tap these, I get absolute in
and absolute out. Here, we'll go to
brighter color
here. Um, a lot of those are kind of
just functional. So, I can, you know,
slow the rig down and kind of move the
whole rig wherever I want it to
go. Um, but then after that, I get into
the more creative, I call them creative
positions, you know. Um, so like this
one I call low fan and X fan
here. Um, and and and while I'm on the
topic of positions, each one of these
positions has a um rotation built in for
the prism. So you can see here if I go
to uh this blind look, the prisms all
rotate into a way where it works with
that position.
Um, so that's kind of a cool feature, I
guess.
Um, those are positions. Um, so what
would I leave off here? Low
fan. Um, here's my trip X,
OpenX. Call this one Pyramid. This one's
Irish Geometry. I mean, some of these
names are like from old versions. I just
kind of kept the names. Uh, Halo, Halo
2, this is called Teeth. This one's
called
Mountains. Uh, and then I have my
cyclls. So in the theater world, a
cycllorama is that back wall.
Um, so if I put a cool look on the goss
here, this first one is kind of like a
direct, you know, try to send them
directly to the wall as I can. Then I've
got a wide one to get as much throw out
of the gobo as possible. And then the
third one is my favorite where they're
all like focused on one point. So like
when I'm focusing this, I just put them
all right in the middle. And then man,
when you turn that prism on, like this
guy, you can you can blow some minds
with this
thing. So, those are my cyc looks. Um,
then I got some other ones that work
really well with the points. I got these
like uh kind of geometric. Uh, this
one's called ghost ball. I used to have
um like a disco ball position and on
rooms and nights when we didn't have a
disco ball, I would still use the
position. And after a while, I was like,
"Oh man, that actually looks pretty cool
on its own." So, you got the uh ghost
ball. This one's called
Crossbones. They look good with the
prism, too. And then this guy is two
stars. You can see why cuz it makes two
stars. Um and then some other more
utility positions for when there is a
disco ball. Clear. This one's not focus.
Uh and then of course I've got one for
each band member. Uh here's Eli and Rob.
And then I got one for the full band and
all that
stuff. Cool. Uh then moving on down on
this side, I've got you saw me using
using them there. I've got my prism or
excuse me, my I call them iris looks,
but on these beam fixtures, it's really
just a gobo. Got tight all the way up to
pretty big and then a big full wash
one. Um then on top of that, I've got
some zoom built in. So like if I'm on a
gobo here, I can zoom that fixture in or
zoom it out. And then the same thing
here for the for the wash lights. can
zoom them all the way in or zoom them
all the way out to get a nice big wash.
Um, so yeah, I've got some band locks
here which lock the lights, lock the
wash lights into certain spots. So that
way I can lock this onto the psych but
still move the beams around and not not
have them move or I can, you know, lock
here on the band, move these
around. Um, and then I got some other
looks here. This is a uh pin spot with
the prisman kind of look. And then I've
got this flat gobo lock. So at any point
I can or I should say flat prism. At any
point I can lock that prism on and move
the rig around. Looks great. Um here are
a whole bunch of goos. So I've got turn
this off here. You know open like cone
gobo here. I'll put these on the back so
you can see them. Kind of a graph paper.
Um I don't even know what you call that.
Lot three lines with the prism on. I
call this one connects. One of my
favorites, the
Triforce. Um, you get the idea. Uh, and
then then here is that Q2 button. Um, so
when I hit the Q2 button and then I
press I'm sorry, this is the round prism
button. This is the Q2 button. Um, so
this is uh turns the circular prism on
and I can go
crazy. Down here I got just your normal
dimmers. So, here I got the
um the low points and the high points,
the upstage wash and the downstage wash.
And then I got room for if I'm on a
bigger rig, uh I can add an extra here.
Um here I've got a left to right kind of
breathey effect, dimmer effect, and then
a random one. The same deal. And then
these are the rates for both chases.
This is the chase rate, and here is the
move rate for these guys.
Cool. What else we got? Okay, so over
here on this on this wing, if you will,
um I got all my strobes. So, this is
like a a color scroll. This is strobing
the wash and this is strobing the the um
the
beams. And then this guy strobes
everything in white. And next up, we've
got the chase section. So, all these
chases follow this chase rate fader. So,
we got a left and then a right and an
in, a random. And then I got some more
like quarter note, eighth note kind of
things. And then this is that really
really fast one. I use this in volume
386, number 86 a lot, you know, to grab
those really fast melodies or
sonic, you know. And then here's uh kind
of the same thing but
mirrored. And then the same concept down
here, but rather than changing shutter
and dimmer like we were up here, we're
we're messing with color. So we get
these like kind of fast blinky color
effects. Okay. So over here to the third
APC, um got what I call color theory. Um
so we go from warm to cool and bright to
dark. So the idea here is that I can
just if I want a if I want a bright blue
look, I click over here and it's kind of
bright and it's blue. Or if I want like
a dark magenta look, I can go down here.
Uh, and they're not, it's not an exact
science, but you get the idea. I can
move around and kind of keep the vibe of
a certain song or section thematically,
if you will. Uh, yeah. Okay. So, moving
on. This this bottom row here, which
would be the the row of actual physical
buttons on an MA uh light or ultra light
or full size. Um, uh, I've got two two
sets here. This over here are my resets.
So, this will reset the beam to open and
this will turn off any effects I have
running. So, like if I had this dimmer
effect running, this will fade two
second fade out of that. Or if I had a
movement effect running, this will stop
the movement effect and fade it all back
down. Okay. Um then over here, I've got
my uh what did we call it earlier? Like
a quantizing fade time section. So, what
I can do is I can click this stop and it
brings all my rates like this to zero.
U. So that's the stop and then the tap I
tap in a tempo and when I click the go
it copies that tap tempo to both of
these fade times. So the effect here is
that I can tap a tempo and then click a
new look and a position with a gobo and
a prism. And then when I hit go I get a
two measure fade. So if it's 1 2 3 4 1 2
3 4 2 2 3 4 boom. So you can get really
really tight fades in time with the
music. And if you tap half time or
double time, it can be, you know, four
measures or one measure. Um, then I got
some more things over here. I've got a
what a twinkle effect as I call it. Uh,
and then I got just a pan
movement, a relative pan movement, a
relative tilt movement. And then this is
a stack of other movement effects. So I
can click the load button to pick one.
say wave. Boom. There's wave. Or if I
wanted to do
uh well, this is a dance ninja. You
know, there got all kinds of weird names
for
them. Um yeah, and then over here I've
got uh this kind of LED breathing
effect. And you saw this one earlier.
This is a color
wheel sine wave effect.
Uh, and this is a focus. Uh, you saw
this a bunch this weekend where I've
got, you know, I used to just kind of
leave the gobo in focus, but they kind
of look really cool when you bust them
out of
focus. Okay, so this is the uh
programmable keyboard. Uh, it's pretty
much all the programmable keys off of a
Grand MA. Um, I got all 20 X keys mapped
down here, and those can be executors
like I have them right now. So like you
know a my show file these are blackouts
and this is like a white or a blackout
wipe. Um I got some bumps. These will
bump on in
thirds. Um and then I have some like LED
color bumps here. So you can do this
kind of
thing. A white frost blowout if you
will. But you can also using these
buttons here set them to be here. Now
they're programming keys. So, these are
MA tricks for aligning and and selecting
the rig and groups and pairs. Um, and
here's some keys for just picking
different groups of fixtures that I use
a lot. And then here on my first view, I
actually have um, uh, views. So, all
these different buttons will go to
different views in the
software. Um, yeah, that's pretty much
it. That's pretty much the right
rundown, I guess. Yeah. Or what did you
ask about programming? So like when you
come in every day, you go through like a
step of program, the focusing and stuff.
Yeah, the focusing in general, but like
you go through you program like your
left, your rights, your ups and downs.
Yeah. Okay. Well, so there's a couple uh
positions in here that we that we I
didn't show you that uh are basically
determine the parameters of the room
here. And I'll I'll show them to you
now. Like this is effects left and this
is effects right and effects up and
effects down. So basically I key those
in each day and then this like this
effect uses those four positions so that
it always looks good like it uses those
as the
parameters. Um and then there's also a
big step in like if I have other house
lights that I'm going to use like for
example the downstage lights here I
clone from lights that I don't actually
own. So I rather than having to spend a
bunch of time programming for these I
just copy the programming over.
How did you decide on the water bottle
trick for Oh, he's talking about the for
you internet people. The way we get to
this one, which is a little off right
now, but every day Nick puts up a water
bottle with gaff tape around it on a mic
stand. I mean, I just needed a something
to point all the lights at and that's
clear so you know when you're there, but
you also know when you're not there, you
know? So it makes focus like because we
just, you know, before we did that, we
would just be like some someone would go
stand down there and tell me what looked
off from where they were and we'd move
each light one. It took forever. Yeah.
And it's like it looks good in most
places, but it's cool to just have it be
right everywhere. So if you're in the
front row looking up at it, they all
meet at one point, you know. Same with
this one. So we need to touch them up
today. Pretty close. What's your
favorite though as far as positioning
goes and or psych? Oh, I mean dude, it
depends on the room, you know, like I
mean of course the psych the psych stuff
is really cool. Like I like this one a
lot uh with the prism on. It seems to be
very psychedelic for lack of a better
word. Like here we put that on with this
effect. That that's a pretty standard
go-to. Also, um, if we go to this glow
sticks look, uh, open the beam, we go to
this guy and go to this look. That's
maybe the like most standard of my
looks. Green beams, purple wash, blue
front wash, cuz, you know, it just looks
it looks like black lights and glow
sticks. That's what it makes me think of
cool. Makes me think of like high
school, you know, like listening to, you
know, fish
and gray music.
Have you talked about some of your color
scheme names? Yeah, I mean, uh, it got
cut out of a bit, so we'll go back over
them. He's talking about the color
theory. Um, here, I'll just go through
them real quick. Put them in or not. So,
we go from warm to cool and from bright
to dark. So, the magenta ones, like I
was saying a minute ago, I treat magenta
as a warm color because it's red and
blue, but it feels warm to me rather
than keep treating it as a cool color.
So, we start with magenta. We've got
Raspberry, Electric
Mayhem, CMY. I mean, not going to go
out. CMY. Uh, this is called Magic Hour.
Um, City Lights. This one's Covenant.
This is a nerdy one. It's kind of like
the Covenant from Halo video game. Uh,
Toad Stool, Red and White, Mario. This
one's
Fireplace. Uh,
Starburst Harvest.
This one's called Dune and it has that
frost built into it. And then here's
that stack I was talking about. Horror
flick and scary movie. Use that a lot in
like Cloud World.
Um, Hot
Sun, Dr. Seuss's Jamboree,
uh, Muerto Deios, which I know is the
improper way to say Day of the Dead, but
whatever. Uh, this one's called
Carbonite. Kind of reminds me of like
Han Solo's being frozen, all that good
stuff. This one's Jedi. Jedi
Temple. Um,
arena. Uh, what else we got here? Soul
Ring is a Magic card. It's definitely
one of the nerdier ones. Uh,
Watermelon, Ocean Sun, Wario, Autumn,
Avocado,
uh,
Starbucks. It's called Summer
94. Little nod to band I happen to like.
Uh, Invader
Zim. Uh, what is this called? Pumpkin
Spice. This is called Cove. It's kind of
like a swampy oceany look.
Doio. They use The guys at Papadosio
have loved this color combo. This kind
of feels like them. So, I named it
Dosio. Um, one of my favorite new ones
that Gabe from uh Consider the Source
actually named is Dagaba. Of course. Of
course I like it. But it this it's got a
nice look to it. It's like kind of cool
but comfortable at the same time. I used
this a lot the other
night.
Danga. Uh this one's the cloud world
look which I actually like to use with
this frost in it without the prism. And
you kind you know you if you blow out
the uh if you blow out
the LED wash
um you get kind of a well looks like
you're in the clouds. It's pretty
self-explanatory. This one's called
Millennium
Falcon. Um, Bestpin or Cloud City, I
guess. This one's called
Rampancy. Her
Place. Uh, number
nine. Uh, and then here's a stack of I
call the stack Earthlike. The first one
is Aldderon, of course, and Pandora and
Aurora.
And some of these have like a long
history, but other other ones are just
who knows why I named it that. This
one's called Wizard. Looks like that
wizard hat from
uh you know the Fantasia. Have you seen
that? It's like a blue hat with the
stars on it. Uh and the second queue in
here is called
Castaway. Um this one's Alchemy. This is
a new one for this tour I happen to like
a
lot.
Um Cotton
Candy. Get the drum out of there. Cotton
Candy,
Subzero, Under the
Sea, Electric Forest,
uh,
Netrunner,
Marshmallow, Fruity Pebbles, even though
they're not Pebbles anymore. Uh, Fall
97,
Moonrise, Transylvania. Kimmel named
this one or he we we're coming up for a
look in the second part of Dracula's
Monk. So yeah, Transylvania uh
Cowabunga, which we talked about
earlier.
Shahuli, Wonka, which I, you know, I
like to use this one for nerds with the
prism. Um Rasta, let's get the Rasta
France of course in French bowling and
rainbow. I got a couple others that
aren't on buttons right now like uh
Dragon and
Hive, Halloween. Where's Halloween?
There. Halloween.
Abyss. Uh Blacklight Party. And then
these are my ones for Turn by Turn if
the band ever plays it again. This one's
called Rubik's Cube. And this one's
called Solved. H. That one's not working
right now. But I used to have it so like
one look like a just like a really
random Rubik's cube and then at the end
when they talk about solving it, it
would look like all like in order.